[Theme Music]
Burnie: But, I had a crazy thing
I thought of you as soon as I had this conversation Gus.
I was in my car
and I got a phone call, and it was from, like Las Vegas, Nevada
I'm like, "I don't know anybody in fucking Las Vegas. Ah, fuck it, I'll answer it."
So I answer my phone. There's a pause and then a woman comes on and she goes,
"Hello, is this Burnie Burns?"
and I said, "Yes it is".
and I immediately knew I was talking to a telemarketer
because I know that pause means...
Gus: ...the call's being connected.
Burnie: Yeah. But she says, "Hello, is this Burnie Burns?" and I go, "Yes it is."
She goes, and this is exactly how she sounded,
[robotically] "I'm calling today to talk to you about your vehicle
which may be eligible for a new extended warranty."
Burnie: And I was like, "Oh god, is this a computer?"
and she goes,
[normal voice] "Oh, do I sound that bad today?"
Burnie: and I was like, "Oh shit!"
[Gavin and Gus laughing]
Burnie: "I'm so sorry!" I said, "That must have been so insulting!"
I said, "I used to run call centers, anyway I apologize."
And just, she laughed, and she goes,
"Ok well the reason I'm calling is about the extended warranty on a vehicle
you might be qualified for an extended warranty."
Burnie: "I know what you're calling about, I get calls about this all the time.
It's my truck, I'm in the process of selling my truck.
So I don't want an extended warranty on it."
She goes, [robotic] "I'm sorry, you don't qualify"
Burnie: "Are you a computer?"
and she goes, "What makes you say that?"
Burnie: "You're not saying no."
she goes, "I guess I'm not."
[Gavin and Gus laughing incredulously]
Burnie: "Can you just answer the question, are you human or are you a computer?"
and she goes, "I'm sorry you don't qualify, thank you."
and hangs up
Gavin: "Oh my god! You don't even know!"
Burnie: I don't know if I talked to a computer or not!
and her first response was, "Do I sound that bad today",
She didn't say no, so it had that built in.
Gavin: So it's a smart robot. You got hung up on by a robot
Burnie: I know. I apologized to a robot, for being rude.
Like I'm sorry, you fucking metal hunk of junk.
[RoosterTeeth Animation Theme]
Gus: If you like this Animated Adventure, subscribe to watch a new one every week.
Check out our merch,
and watch our other videos.
You wanna stare at my cleavage?
Oh, I'm not girl Gus? Fuck.