I'll on
theme
are
are our rights are finally over nova
K for the I gotta
certain friend come down you
contain yourself can do no with purely
partisan the proscan oh my god this is
why no one shows up
fanfictions what we have had today's
challenge
or whatever week of I don't know why I
keep calling a challenge band we are
going to create each other
at
air on OK Cupid which is a dating site
and the challenge
is that whoever gets the most dick pics
had what sir our next month well drained
I wasn't feeling bad about bass at all
has noticed I think he hung up I
know he's is a nap if I and then if I
said I have known if I send my own does
that count as well over
certainly a there yet you can ask your
friends to be whatever you why
there's no rule on okay but them
demos amount a dick pics well when side
taking the liberty
are photoshopping each one of us as a
female
so we're gonna say we can 10 years your
picture
no I
and can now are sure to catch I
are you holding a candle for Brees you
know
I
so in case someone doesn't like how can
looks like
and know at least that again can offer a
great cleaning
methods me okay gonna go in my picture
next rich I didn't do myself
a fan did this one ALG II an
I look like I
ass pretty good like you look at it the
African psycho girl from Silent Hill 2
that bike stab you
last but not least well but and you did
this
I would brace myself for this one I
answer ready a good I could not find a
fucking picture would be the without the
beard
okay I had to give you some features
at that I would compensate
then the beard I am pared its
go hurt
0 mana
I on I
I'm not change anything in the phase
it's a when a guy
the bonus so we'll see how that goes a
Merry America areas how
a big cleavage there's actually this
bitch is floating around me dressed as a
girl anyway cuz I i mean I've done it
before
getting may have got it before I guess
it out there
I do that every be yeah I'll
we ever gonna go on air only K ok
Airways go OK Cupid a dating website and
we're gonna create each other's profiles
a
but yes go ahead and upload I'll do from
person to each I think you should turn
over since a you give a gal do know
magician boobies account in oven so then
what am I i said i said you can
yeah I had which I read fanfictions
right there
I got sick and Indian you have a lot of
people in the US is this
whatever's going to get less or more
dick pics alright so
can you're gonna be like sixty years old
sorry
me I us yeah but when I scotteri
615 you know what a certain appeal in
you know your own I'm a delicate flower
our dad I didn't think when I created
this
might my username I rode pretty pie and
it suggested pupae a Saurus
so okay that's your name now you live in
New York your 25-year-old woman
at
and you lack
you love to me strangers
with pictures of you won't believe it
but the username no hair no problem is
teh I
sexy going for a well how about that
British pilot a into a mirror and about
it
well-mannered right now you're bisexual
female
in your boy around the time a
Valentine's Day
Kane a my username be immune
you matter that matters this will be
public archive
use names similar penis password yes
please
their ERA together
passers two-week carry on about me
I but
how was your best friend describe you
me there is come on gimme
give them again some people all know
think am crazy but I'm not crazy
I but is not gonna take place I
I'm only crazy
about love dick pics
affect rather than creating a pic enact
I am have to hide it
I a I'm really good at
giving naughty itself be favorite books
fifty Shades of Grey ken Spencer
actually cropped in pretty good like
yeah he get the for Brees and everything
out so much the toilet %ah
I guess what as my best features a
toilet fix things I could never
do that without my vibrator
and my other five Lawal I it's ok and
you're bound me
is all about your hair K and this isn't
isn't just hair on your head
so I put some would say the hair is bad
but I say let us clear the path for hair
hair is the most natural ingredient in
the human body
it works well in soup and just as well
in Sala
burning hair also creates the
utmost Roddick a Rome K
you're really good at Daves yeah
I I wanna send a pic students yeah
missus much how I would produce ok
dice DPK 71 said in my profile
you I yeah
so funny IIT she says it isn't here
oh my god a man oh what
am I supposed to be getting a buncha
dudes from
from oh they're really old people that
are coming up for can right now
yeah I yeah
region ignition the all the desperate
one shed Kevin Dyson patted my back
I mean I think it's big it's its it's
all for Denver's well like it's going
off from where I live in
me how much I def guys here your money
into their match at the market
both all to people like me things are
heating up
hello I need to change your focus your
cleavage
barely showing no
yeah you have to like make a big a yeah
kenna my getting any visitors no
no one loves you actually had one when
one lady came by to see what's up
as far as someone who has my name smear
peers I
howdy how do you see like where the
visitors are all here that is known as
the dear
hobby Chennai know has life
I am well it's something rare recanted
down with the profiles
dorgan so hard on the other and get
along too and it is now some stuff so
now they're
Nova has three fucking likes relay
yes I don't seattle City Light Fix
alway there's it says who likes you and
I don't have anybody there
yet well maybe you don't have a giant
fucking kleevage
alright I it's gotta be kansas session
with hair that's the on a
okay well
we're gonna check in mail next week to
see year who got
the best have traction promos depicts
and I think a chest hairs okay is going
to be pretty good
I mean he sixty-eight years old
a typical Friday night Felix watch
Netflix and passing kidney stones
of us is a assist first RK
its it sound like I'm going to win
there's already I
just left the scene the next month fish
are the No
I'll
%uh