[theme music]
[applause and cheering]
STEPHEN COLBERT: Welcome to
The Report everybody,
thank you so much for
joining us.
[applause and cheering]
Thank you so much.
[Crowd chanting: Stephen!
Stephen! Stephen!]
Thank you so much ladies
and gentlemen.
FR. TOM: I'm overcome with
emotion, being here in
this chair, normally I can
handle this, but when I see
who's in front of me in this
particular episode of WITNESS,
I say, "Mein Gott!"
Or, "Mama mia!" Stephen Colbert
is with us, here on WITNESS,
so thank you for making
the time for us-
Watch your language Father,
this is a family show.
[Fr. Tom chuckles]
Now, which Stephen Colbert is
sitting in the chair here?
COLBERT: You know-
FR. TOM: Is this Stephen Colbert
of The Colbert Report?
Or is this a new Stephen
Colbert? Are you born again?
COLBERT: Well- wow.
That's ambitious. Um-
That's a good question, because
when people invite me
to do things, I don't-
I don't always know who
they've invited,
me or the guy on the
television show.
So who are you?
COLBERT: This is me.
This is me.
FR. TOM: So this is like the
presentation of Stephen Colbert
to the world.
Uh, yes.
FR. TOM: The new Stephen,
born again Stephen.
COLBERT: Um, yes, I mean
that- boy,
I- certainly out of his cocoon.
I changed my Twitter handle from
@stephencolbert,
like host of The Colbert Report,
to @stephencolbertpolliwog,
because after the last show
was over,
I felt like I went back to
a tadpole form.
You know, and I wanted to,
I wanted to like lose my arms
and legs, and grow a tail
and have a- you know, a fleshy
sac around me,
filled with amniotic fluid,
because I really do need to
lose old habits from the old
show to the new show,
so, yeah, born again, that
sounds great Father.
FR. TOM: Now before we bury you,
I am intrigued to look at that
previous character,
because it's a character,
obviously that's captivated
the imagination of the world-
Right, what do you want
to know about him Father?
Who's asking and why? Okay.
FR. TOM: I'm asking- This is-
Just because you got the dog
collar on doesn't mean
you know more about
the Catholic Church than I do,
you understand me?
Are we clear on that?
I learned a couple weeks ago
you know a hell of a lot
about the Catholic Church.
I know one or two things,
I'm not going to say I'm a-
a Basilian, you're a
Basilian right?
A Basilian, yeah.
COLBERT: St. Basil?
FR. TOM: We're many, Basilians.
COLBERT: Okay?
St. Basil?
FR. TOM: St. Basil.
COLBERT:
I'm no fan, okay?
FR. TOM: Why?
COLBERT: St. Arugula,
that's the saint.
FR. TOM: St. Arugula-
That's the saint I worship,
okay?
Delicious.
St. Arugula-
COLBERT: With a little St. Pine
Nut, little St. Reggiano-
Yeah, St. Grappa's lovely too.
COLBERT: St. Grappa,
I have worshipped.
[Fr. Tom laughing]
COLBERT: I have worshipped the
porcelain throne of St. Grappa.
[Fr. Tom laughing]
I haven't.
You haven't?
Now tell me something,
why is it my whole staff at
Salt + Light Television,
when they knew I was going to be
doing this interview,
they went wild. They said,
"Father,
this is bigger than anything
you've ever done,
this is bigger than three popes
together!"
So I asked them, I said, "What
the heck's big about this?"
I watched some of those
programs, I mean it's-
it's an incredible program that
he did, nine years-
COLBERT: Yeah.
FR. TOM: -of The Colbert Report.
Who was that character? What
created that character?
COLBERT: That character
was, first of all,
can I go back, you just said
bigger than three popes.
You can't be bigger than
three popes,
you can only be bigger
than two popes,
that's the most we've ever
had at one time.
Oh except during Avignon,
I guess,
there were three popes at
one point, right?
FR. TOM: That's right, what do
you think- I know my history.
COLBERT: Okay, I apologise.
Forgive me Father,
for I doubted you. Thank you
very much.
[Fr. Tom laughing]
That guy was, we like to
describe him as-
well he was a pundit,
first of all,
and pundits are creatures
of pure opinion,
not necessarily fact,
but feelings,
what they feel is true.
And we like to describe him as a
well-intentioned, which was
really important to me,
well-intentioned, poorly
informed, not a very
curious person, high status,
in other words he
assumed the high ground on
every argument, idiot,
and the idiot
is kind of the hardest part of
it because
it sounds pejorative to say
"idiot", but idiocy is actually-
or foolishness is another way
to say it, a fool,
is really a hard thing to
consistently achieve,
as a performer.
Like when we're rewriting any
show, whether it was my old show
or any show I've worked on,
as a comedian,
you'll be sitting around trying
to think of the right joke,
and someone will say,
"Well I have an idea."
"What is it?" Because you're on
a deadline,
the clock is ticking. And-
and the person will go,
"Well- oh I don't know,
it's stupid."
And we'd go, "How stupid?"
[laughing]
COLBERT: Because stupid
is like gold, because
to think illogically is,
you know, is-
to think illogically is often
just to think unexpectedly,
and we perceive it as stupid,
but that, you know,
it's boring to talk about what
makes something funny,
but that change up between
your expectation
and what somebody- the way
someone behaves,
in a joke or in a scene, is
often where the comedy happens,
or where the satire happens.
And so,
he's a fool because he doesn't
act according to logic,
and he also doesn't act
according to social norms,
and he doesn't act according to
social expectations,
or expectations of what a human
reaction would be.
It's funny to talk about this
with a priest,
because when I would have
people on the show,
who I'd met, men of the cloth,
of any faith,
or people who I knew were of a-
of at least a
deep or overt faith, if that was
part of their public persona
that we knew about them,
I would- I would
often go back to talk to them,
and instead of saying, you know,
he's a well-intentioned,
poorly informed,
high status idiot, I would say,
"He's a fool."
And though Christ says, "Call no
man fool, I am one." And so-
Aren't we all fools for Christ,
huh?
[exhales]
Yeah, yeah, willing to be
wrong in society,
or wrong according to our time,
but right according to
our conscience,
which is guided by
the Holy Spirit.
FR. TOM: Now, how long-
COLBERT: Are you writing
this down by the way?
Because I'm laying it, this is-
FR. TOM: We're recording-
COLBERT: I mean, I should have
this in Latin, what I just said.
I'm sending all of this to Rome,
right away, so don't worry.
COLBERT: Please.
FR. TOM: Tell me something,
for each of those episodes,
and I watched several of them-
All 1,447 I hope.
FR. TOM: Several-
COLBERT: Several.
FR. TOM: How long did it take to
prepare one episode?
Like, how many people are
working with you to produce
that character, and that
episode?
Uh, let's see.
Some shows we wrote in a day,
and that was very hard to do,
'cause to do a half hour show,
creating it in a single day
would be really hard.
Uh, there are, including crew,
all in, about 90 people
who worked on the last show.
On the next show I'm working on,
there's going to be
nearly 200 people-
For The Late Show-
COLBERT: For The Late Show,
on CBS.
Um, there's going to be
nearly 200 people:
a dozen writers,
another handful, four or five
people who are
producers and also writers,
in other words they're part of
an editorial staff that is
cutting, collating, punching up
scripts, polishing them,
getting them to that final form
so that I can say to them,
I'm one of those people.
Um, we have-
I have producers who are, we say
in our booking department,
in our guest department, who-
work with me as to what
sort of people
I would want to talk to, um,
Emily Lazar, who is my
co-executive producer,
I've worked with her for years,
she knows the kind of people
who interest me.
Um, hopefully people who
represent something, or an idea,
aren't merely famous.
Um- and we have
a production department
that is actually doing
the nuts and bolts, literally
paying the bills, hiring
the caterers, feeding everybody,
keeping the lights on,
making sure it gets broadcast.
We have the crew shooting
the camera,
you have the people in
the control shooting the-
we have the cameramen
shooting the show,
you got people in the control
room doing the sound,
sequencing all the graphics,
all the video,
you've got a graphics
department creating
what you see over my shoulder,
or the graphics on
the lower screen,
or the editors creating
the roll-in films
that we do on the show. Um-
I envy, I covet my
neighbour here.
Yeah. But it's a- you know,
it's a whole lot people,
hopefully pulling on the same
rope, and-
And the really nice thing about
doing it every day
is that you do your best to
get it right, but-
you know, it's like Kleenex,
there's another one in the box,
and you'll get it tomorrow.
What I found interesting,
there's even a play on words,
of the show. Now, as a teacher
of French,
I would say, "C'est le Rapport
du Monsieur Colbert."
Mais oui.
FR. TOM: And you called it
the Colbert "Rapport",
it wasn't The Colbert Report,
but "Rapport". And-
what was behind all that?
COLBERT: Well first of all, we
thought it would sound
more pretentious.
[Fr. Tom laughing]
So you can- it'll play
in Quebec.
My character's high status
remember,
my character that I played
at the old show
was really high status, and so,
we thought what would be
more pretentious than to A) Have
a pretentious name
like "Colbert", where you don't
pronounce the "T",
especially to an American ear,
I don't know about a-
a Canadian ear, but to
an American ear,
anything that sounds French
is a little, you know,
is a little snooty, a little
frou-frou. And so, um-
But I'm Colbert, I was born
Colbert, my father's a Colbert,
my brothers and sisters
are Colbert,
I'm one of 11 kids and half of
us are Colbert
and half of us are Colbert,
because my father said,
"You can choose what you want."
So, I chose Colbert,
because I'm essentially
a pretentious person,
and- so we thought, "Well let's-
how can we increase
that pretentiousness?
Well let's make it-
let's make the word after me,
'Report', to say 'Rapport',"
and- you know, and
Bob's your uncle,
that's how we got the name of
the show, but it also is
a play on words,
because as a pundit,
you know the people I was
modeling myself on,
their relationship to their
audience is sort of like,
you know, "You watch my show,
therefore, you know,
you're the heroes, you get
what's going on in the world,
because I'm telling you what's
going on in the world, and
together we're going
to fix things."
And that attitude of like, you-
we, we're the it-getters,
that sense of rapport was just
another play on words
on the title of the show,
not a great play on words.
FR. TOM: How difficult was it
over a period of nine years to
maintain that character,
to stay in character?
COLBERT: Oh, most difficult
actually when I was
talking to guests whose subjects
I was really interested in,
because he- he's
willfully ignorant,
he's not just ignorant,
he's willfully ignorant because
he knows that
willful ignorance
allows you to win
arguments you otherwise wouldn't
because you can be
selective about your own facts,
and still be
honest with yourself.
If I choose not to learn what
things are like in reality,
I can say, trickle-down
economics works,
because it feels like
it would, right?
You know, if you just fill
my bucket enough,
eventually it's going to
dribble on you,
you're welcome, you're welcome
for that dribble,
there's more to come. Um- but
it would help if I don't
actually find out
what life is like for the poor,
would help if I don't find out
what the history of trickle-down
economics is,
and that willful ignorance
allows me to win
that argument honestly, because
I just don't know otherwise.
He's not malicious, he was
well-intentioned.
And it was hardest to maintain
that sense of ignorance,
or to maintain that foolish
behaviour,
in the face of people whose
subject I really enjoyed,
like my friend Neil deGrasse
Tyson, um-
Fr. Jim Martin, um-
because if I really liked their
subject, it would be hard to-
it would be hard to maintain my-
my game of embodying
common ignorances,
because I wanted to engage them
on their subject
in an honest and passionate way,
but that wasn't my job.
My job was actually to really
allow them to dispel
common ignorances about their
subject by- by being-
by standing them up,
for my guests,
so they can knock them down,
and the only time I was
frustrated by that, really,
is when my guest wouldn't
realize I was doing it.
[Fr. Tom laughing]
And they would let me win,
I didn't want to win,
I wanted my guest to win,
but sometimes, I guess the force
of the personality
of the character I was playing
would steamroll them, so-
I'm sorry, it's over now.
[applause and cheering]
Folks, the 2016
Presidential election
is almost upon us, and I for one
cannot wait to see
who the American people elect
next for John Boehner to sue.
[audience laughing]
Of course, former First Lady,
former Senator,
and former Secretary of State
Hillary Clinton is
the current frontrunner,
which is surprising
since it sounds like she can't
hold down a job.
[audience laughing]
FR. TOM: You had a great
political satire
that was going on, your
commentary on politics,
your commentary on the
American government,
on politicians.
Are there limits to
political satire,
are there limits to-
Oh, yeah sure, I mean it
depends on what you mean
the goal of political satire is.
Well what is the goal?
In your mind,
what was the goal of
political satire?
COLBERT: To make people laugh.
You know, I would make jokes
about politics because
my model was the news, and
I care about politics,
and I care about- I care about
current events,
and I'll always do jokes
about that,
I mean the new show has that
as well, we're definitely-
that's a big part of
the new show,
especially going into a
Presidential election. But-
the goal is to make people
laugh, I mean
politics is incredibly
frustrating, the news can be
incredibly depressing, if we
just make your day
a little bit better, you know,
at the end because we-
we make jokes that shows, yeah
we feel the same way you do,
or like, or rather we curate
for you our feelings
about the news, and maybe you
agree with our jokes
or what's funny about
the day's news.
That sense of connection between
the performer and the audience
is the entire intention,
you know, why does anybody-
why does anybody-
what does anybody want?
Not to be alone,
and I think a performer gets
onstage and says the things
that are in his mind, in his
own particular way,
to make a connection
with an audience
so he doesn't feel so alone.
And hopefully the audience feels
the same way, you know,
it's not conscious,
it's here, it's not here. And-
so that's got to be the goal,
that connection has got to be
the goal, and the-
making somebody laugh has
got to be the goal.
You can't think
that your- your
satire is going to
change things.
Peter Cook famously said,
great satirist,
worked with Dudley Moore,
and uh-
in Beyond the Fringe,
he famously said that
the greatest satire of the 20th
Century was the Weimar cabaret,
and boy they just stopped Hitler
in their tracks.
You know- you know,
you can't imagine that
however great your joke is
that it's gonna
change things, what it does is-
just make a connection
with an audience who's feeling
the same way you do.
FR. TOM: You had a great way of
talking about religion
as well, about- you're Catholic,
everybody knows you're Catholic,
you were able to make fun
of the Catholic Church,
I mean I watched some
of those episodes
and just burst out laughing,
and you got away with it!
I'm so glad.
FR. TOM: And at times I heard
you say some comments about-
COLBERT: I would sometimes
scoot around my priest,
at the end of Mass,
I was kind of like-
"Hi Father!" I'd just leave.
They were very nice about it.
But you had a way of doing it
where you didn't-
you didn't cross a line, but you
made us laugh at ourselves,
and not to take ourselves
too seriously.
Well that would be nice, I hope
so, I mean I hope so.
I didn't want to- you know,
I didn't want to make-
I don't ever,
I mean I'll still make jokes
about the Church,
I'll make jokes about anything,
you can't make-
you can't- as long as you're not
being malicious,
I don't think you can leave
anything off the table.
I- I wouldn't want to
make jokes-
it wouldn't feel right for me,
it wouldn't feel good for me,
it wouldn't be obeying my own
conscience, I suppose,
to make jokes about
the sacraments,
or specifically the Eucharist, I
mean the other sacraments,
for some reason don't feel as-
well they're not Christ himself,
but um- so, like-
like a nacho cheese Eucharist
joke- not-
FR. TOM: You wouldn't
go there, good.
You know, like- you know,
there's plenty in that realm
that I don't want to do
that joke-
FR. TOM: Don't go to church
that Sunday.
COLBERT: Yeah, exactly.
Um, but-
I mean, the Church is an
important part of my life,
I would be crazy if I didn't
make jokes about it.
But one thing my character had,
and I had in common,
is that, yeah, we both
are Catholics, and
he just feels like a victim
about it, all the time.
FR. TOM: And you wore it
on your sleeve,
you were happy to do so.
Yeah, happy to, yeah.
FR. TOM: What did you think, as
a major figure in television-
COLBERT: Yeah.
FR. TOM: When-
COLBERT: The major
figure in television-
The- excuse me, "the",
I forgot the article,
when you saw the terrible things
happen in Paris,
with Charlie Hebdo-
Oh my God, I was-
FR. TOM: What was going on
inside of you, because
in a sense, you were
able to show us
that if we love our religion,
we're able to laugh at it,
and then we saw the tragedy
happen in Paris,
and "Je suis Charlie",
and everything else,
what did you think?
Well first of all,
shocked and horrified that this
would happen to people
for any- any public expression,
regardless of
how anyone might be
offended by it.
Shocking and horrific, and-
really struck on- there's
no sufficient-
there's no sufficient response
I could've thought of
at that moment, and I felt very
lucky not to be on-air
at that time, to- to have to-
often when a big story happens,
I would think,
"I wish I were on-air to talk
about this," that one was like,
"I'm so glad I'm not because I
don't have anything
I think that approaches-
approaches it." Because also,
you know, finding humour in
the tragedy of horror,
of others, is you know- not
my job. Matter of fact,
it's actually part of my job
to have the-
discretion not to do that,
to know when not to do that. Um-
so that was my first reaction
was, it was kind of
a selfish one, which was,
"I'm so glad
I don't have to be on-air right
now." Um- but-
the second reaction was,
you know,
if this were the 14th Century,
Christians could have done this.
If the 15th Century Christians
might have been offended
to the point of violence,
at blaspheme.
You know, check your history
books. So, in an ultimate sense,
I do not perceive- I don't
perceive that-
that action, as indicative of
Islam, but-
so I'm not trying to make a
moral equivalency between
the Christianity of the Middle
Ages and these people,
who are doing this horror
right now, but
every religion has
been so defensive of its beliefs
that it has actually abandoned
its beliefs at times.
And-
that we now, that I could do my
show and make jokes,
about the Church, and now
sit with a priest
and laugh about it, that's a
fairly modern behaviour.
It's a form of-
COLBERT: That's not a
hundred year-old,
that's not a hundred year old
behaviour,
this is a modern behaviour,
this is- I hope,
the right relationship to have
with your faith,
which is to love it, but not
to exclude it from
your intellect.
It's also a form of maturity
too, in faith.
COLBERT: I hope so.
FR. TOM: That people who believe
can be mature enough
that you love something so much,
that you're able to also
make light of some things.
COLBERT: Uh, Carl Sagan
once said that,
"Buddhists believe their God
is so great
that he need not
actually exist."
[Fr. Tom laughing]
COLBERT: Which I think
is a- which is a really-
I really like that because
it reminds me of
St. Anselm of Canterbury's
ontological argument
for the existence of God,
about, you know,
"The fool says in his heart that
there is no God,
but by God, he means that being
then which no greater being
can be conceived." And then it
goes into this lovely
13-step proof that God
must exist because
we conceive of the Word.
It's logically perfect,
it's completely unsatisfying.
Faith ultimately can't be
argued, faith has to be felt.
And hopefully you can still feel
your faith fully,
and let your mind have a logical
life of its own,
and they do not defy each other,
but complement each other,
because logic itself, I don't
think, for me, and you know-
Aquinas might say differently.
Logic itself will not
lead me to God.
But my love of the world, and my
gratitude toward it, will.
And, so, hopefully I can use my
mind to make my jokes,
and not deny my love for God
at the same time.
FR. TOM: Let me ask you a
question, the founder of
your Church and the founder of
my Church, this Palestinian Jew
of the 1st Century named Jesus-
Yeah.
FR. TOM: When I- I
teach Scripture,
I know a lot about Jesus and
what he's done, but one thing
I don't find in the
New Testament
is that Jesus laughed, he told-
COLBERT: No! It did say
Jesus wept,
that's tough for a comedian.
FR. TOM: It's the shortest line.
COLBERT: Nowhere does it
say that Jesus, you know-
He laughed-
COLBERT: Guffawed.
FR. TOM: Yeah he sat around- I
can't imagine him sitting around
the Sea of Galilee, with fish
and some drinks-
COLBERT: No, uh-uh.
FR. TOM: -with a bunch of his
motley crew-
But he had to, right?
Yeah, how can he not?
COLBERT: He's fully man right?
Fully God, fully man?
But it doesn't say that
he laughed or smiled,
do you believe that?
COLBERT: No, but- but wait
a second. No,
nowhere does it say,
"Jesus busted a gut."
[Fr. Tom laughing]
COLBERT: Judas, it does say
Judas busted a gut!
FR. TOM: It certainly did.
COLBERT: That's, yeah.
Um- but, here's where
I think Jesus
had to have been laughing.
Where?
Or at least smiling-
COLBERT: Is, uh- were they off
of Capernaum or something,
'cause it's Peter- Capernaum
is Peter's hometown right?
So, Sea of Galilee,
there's a storm,
the fishermen are out there,
Peter-
his brother's Andrew, is that
what it is?
Yeah, yeah.
COLBERT: Anyways, out there
with the other Apostles,
or just other fishermen, storm,
they don't know what to do,
they see Jesus walking across
the water toward them,
calming the waves around him as
he goes, and Peter, you know,
he does his best-
[Colbert chuckles]
And he thinks- he takes a risk,
he goes, "Well- if I believe,
I can do that too."
So he throws a leg over, goes to
walk across the water,
and he does it for a little bit.
But then he looks down,
loses faith and drops,
and I just-
I have to imagine that that
looked like Wile E. Coyote
running too far off a cliff,
and then- going about
40 feet off from the cliff
and then going-
[imitates Wile E. Coyote
falling]
And falling down
into the canyon.
If Jesus didn't laugh then,
then I'm in big trouble,
because that's the God
I worship.
FR. TOM: You know, one of the-
good. One of the scenes-
'cause I look at this and-
COLBERT: 'Cause when he
comes over and he says, "Oh-"
I'm paraphrasing,
can I paraphrase?
It's the 21st Century, no one's
going to burn me-
FR. TOM: You're allowed to
with me.
COLBERT: I'm going to
paraphrase the Gospel right now,
mistranslating it, basically it
says, "Why'd you look down?
Oh you of little faith. Just
keep your eyes on me,"
because when he had
his eyes on Christ,
all things were possible,
but when he looked at the actual
trouble, he fell.
FR. TOM: You know another time
I think he laughed,
'cause I've had to go through
the New Testament,
people have said, "He never
smiled, he didn't laugh,
don't make him into that."
When he got to Jericho, he's
walking along the big crowd,
and there's this guy climbing up
a tree,
hanging out of a tree.
Can you imagine Jesus standing
at the bottom of that tree,
"Zacchaeus, what in God's name
are you doing? Get down here.
I'm coming to your house for a
blast tonight," you know?
And they said, "No, no,
he didn't laugh,
he was reprimanding him."
I said, "Jesus laughed,
he smiled." Humour is a
really important thing.
Sure, sure.
Now we've talked before
about humour,
and I want you to tell me
a little bit,
what's your understanding
of humour?
Why is humour important for
the human condition?
We got a lot of people walking
around the world today saying,
"The world is bad, the Church is
bad, everything is bad,
we're going to hell
in a hand basket."
What's your role in humour?
Well on one level, humour's
a release valve,
of tension. You know, the world
doesn't make sense
to us sometimes, and the
incongruity of jokes
actually is like a release: you
reproduce the incongruity
you see in the life that you
wish was happening but isn't,
and you create that incongruity
in a joke, and the-
the parallel feeling of those
two makes you laugh, boy,
that was an hilarious
explanation of humour.
[Fr. Tom laughing]
COLBERT: But I think the most
important thing is-
is it's a communication tool,
it's used to communicate to
somebody else about the
incongruities of life.
And-
C.S. Lewis, whose apologetics
I really enjoy reading
when I was younger especially-
FR. TOM: Great guy.
COLBERT: He has, in
The Screwtape Letters,
he talks about awe and humour.
And he says that there are
four different types of humour,
and one is-
or four things that
produce laughter,
and it's one devil advising
another devil,
that's the premise of
The Screwtape Letters,
for those who haven't read them
out there, they're really-
they're really great. And,
Screwtape is writing to his
nephew Wormwood,
who is a demon in training,
about how to get the clients,
which is us, to their
infernal father,
and away from the clutches of
the enemy, who is God.
And so he says, "Now listen,
I understand your patient,
your client is laughing a lot.
This won't necessarily help us,
you see.
We think that this will help us,
but there are many things
that produce laughter,
one is joy," and he goes,
"Joy might be the laughter
produced by old friends,
or family, who haven't seen
each other in a long time.
This is related to play.
These things
are a music that we can't hear,
and-
but is played by the enemy,"
that brings joy
to these peoples' lives.
The second one is, um-
the second one is play, that's
the second one, play,
like the laughter that's
produced by doing something
in common together, and perhaps
doing it well,
or a game of some kind.
The third one is
the joke proper,
which of course is the one that
concerns me as a humourist.
The joke proper um, can, um-
can be about things
that are virtuous,
but the joke proper itself is
not necessarily a sin,
because even making a joke
about virtue
takes intellectual sweat, which
is itself a gift from God
that people are using.
The thing that produces humour,
or the thing that
produces laughter that will help
the Devil, is flippancy.
In flippancy, no joke is
actually made.
The attitude that a joke
has been made
is copped by everybody there.
It does not increase affection,
it distances people,
it armours the soul against joy,
and it deadens the intellect-
This is a philosophy course,
this is great!
COLBERT: Well, it's a great
article, and if, you know,
if someone is interested in-
in religion, or Christian life,
and interested in humour at the
same time, read that essay
because it's a great guide post,
it's very easy
to pretend like you're making
a joke with people
who also want to pretend
they're making jokes,
and if you're flippant,
that is the-
it is the opposite of joy. And-
you know, here's a- here's
a purpose of humour,
or of laughter really, because
humour's a soft term,
I've said this before, but
you can't laugh and be afraid
at the same time,
and I don't mean that, like
mentally you can't hold
both things, it's somehow
like autonomic.
It's somehow physical. I think
that's one of the reasons
why I'll be like, we laugh when
we're afraid,
our body's trying to get rid of
that feeling inside of us,
but if you're laughing,
you know, you-
you just won't be afraid, which
is why it is so important
to laugh at the Devil. You know,
I forgot who said it,
it might've been Milton who
says, "You must laugh
at the Devil because by mockery
alone he cannot abide."
FR. TOM: You know, I always say
that several years ago,
a certain President of the
United States went to Iraq
looking for the weapons of
mass destruction,
and didn't find them. We have
the gift of mass construction,
it's called joy, it's a
dangerous weapon.
And sometimes against
the most horrific things
that have happened in our lives,
and the world,
the best thing that can happen
sometimes is laughter,
and a smile, and joy. It's-
Joy is super important.
We, at the old show, and
hopefully the new show,
you know, we're just starting
up, we used to call it
"The Joy Machine"-
[Fr. Tom laughing]
COLBERT: -because, especially
when it was really hard,
like on those days that,
you know,
doing a show all year round
because we do-
we do 200 shows a year, and
it's really hard to do that,
but you don't want to
bank down your ambitions, so
you'll do a really hard show,
in a really hard schedule, and
somehow when it was hardest,
it would often feel
the most joyful,
or often does feel
the most joyful. And-
and that's when I would sort of
jokingly call it
"The Joy Machine", but it's
sort of true because
the only way to approach
something that's really hard,
it's got to be with joy, because
if you don't approach it
with joy, it's just a machine,
and it'll grind you up,
and the lesson that I took from
that is that
doing something joyfully doesn't
make it any easier,
it only makes it better. And
also, it makes it communal,
that we're all doing it
together.
When you work in fear, or when
you work in, you know,
in distress, you often
feel alone,
but jokes, laughter,
humour, joy,
whatever you want to call it,
it connects people
and, as I said earlier, what do
we want to be? Not alone.
Speaking of "The Joy Machine",
we got this guy running our
Church right now, Pope Francis-
I'm familiar.
FR. TOM: You've seen him,
you kind of saw him
in pictures and stuff?
Sure, sure, I get US Magazine.
[laughing]
FR. TOM: He writes his first
Apostolic letter called
Evangelii Gaudium-
COLBERT: Sure, I took my Latin,
yeah.
FR. TOM: It doesn't mean-
The message of joy-
FR. TOM: The Gospel of Joy,
yeah.
What do you think about Pope
Francis? Where does his-
I think he's pretty joyful,
where do you think
it comes from?
Oh I don't know,
I don't presume to know exactly,
but I-
FR. TOM: What do you think?
Well I assume that it is a gift
of the Holy Spirit. Um-
you know, my favourite- and I've
said this to your friend,
Jim Martin, is that my favourite
passage from the Gospel is,
"So I say to you do not worry,
for whom among you by worrying
could change a hair on his head,
or add a cubit
to the span of his life," that
sort of thing. Um- and-
the opposite of worry is joy,
you know, the opposite of
fear, or anger, is peace, the
opposite of fear would be
laughter. Um, so I assume that
he takes the Gospel to heart,
and does not worry.
When people are angry I think
mostly they're afraid. And,
if you take that particular
passage, which is my favourite,
it's from the sermon, when you
can't go wrong in the sermon,
it's all hits. It's like
The Beatles,
it's The Beatles of the Bible.
FR. TOM: Like, like, like, like-
Exactly, just check everybody
off, swipe-
which one's Tinder? Swipe right?
I swipe right on all that stuff.
So if you take that line
of the Gospel to heart,
I mean it's hard, you know,
it's hard,
then I think, you've got a much
better chance
of living in joy, because you
live in acceptance,
you're not afraid of what's
going to happen to you.
You know, and what I like about
it is that Christ doesn't say,
"Try not to worry." He says, "Do
not- so I say to you," comma,
or colon, however they would do
it in Aramaic-
[laughing]
COLBERT: "Do not worry,"
it's close to a commandment.
And given such hope by this
pope, "Pope hope",
because that's the Church that
I want, that's-
when he said in his opening-
when he said in his-
I think it was, was it the first
sermon that he gave?
After being made pope in the-
that papal audience room,
where he said, "I want this to
be a Church-
a poor Church for the poor."
FR. TOM: "Una chiesa dei poveri:
I want a Church for the poor,
a Church of the poor."
Now you're just bragging
that you can speak Italian.
[laughing]
FR. TOM: I was there!
I was there!
COLBERT: Padre, uno italiano
e morto cavi,
to ma voglio parlare meglio.
[Fr. Tom laughing]
Bravo?
FR. TOM: Bravissimo.
I don't have to translate this
part into Italian.
COLBERT: Mille grazie,
mille grazie padre.
Um, that gave- that made me
so excited!
I think, you know, one of
the reasons why-
and listen, I'm a wealthy man,
don't get me wrong,
but one of the reasons why we
don't help the poor,
I think is that we think if
we give it to them,
we won't have anything,
you know,
so again it's fear that keeps
you from experiencing the joy
of helping other people. So,
I really like this pope,
you know, I'm gonna- I'm gonna-
you know,
I like this pope because
it seems like-
I believe the Church has always
had a message of love,
it's not like I'm somebody like,
"The Church is different now!"
I love my Church, you know,
it's not like I don't have-
I don't share-
You love it, you're in church,
you teach CCD-
COLBERT: Now listen, let's not
go overboard with that stuff.
I go to church, you know,
I do go to church,
and I have taught CCD, you know,
I taught three years of it
over the last nine years,
not every year, um,
but I am no particular exemplar
of my faith,
I just happen to have affection
for my Church, and I love, um-
the opportunity, the traditions
that my Church give me
to contemplate the message
of Christ,
and that's a complicated way
of saying it, but that's-
FR. TOM: No, I got it.
COLBERT: -that's- like the
action of the Mass itself
I enjoy, because I love
the recapitulation
of the Last Supper. I really
like it, it actually makes-
it makes the idea of-
the Eucharist, uh-
well the physical action of it
makes the Eucharist
real for me, though I got to
tell you, you know,
and, I don't know, take this
with some salt and light-
FR. TOM: Thank you. That's in
the sermon too.
COLBERT: Is that when I felt the
Eucharist was most real to me
was a time I didn't receive it.
Is that I was actually at an
Anglican Church-
FR. TOM: Yeah.
And- uh, you know, no offense,
I was at an Anglican Church and
a female priest
was saying the Mass, and it was
a High Anglican Mass,
and so the words were
almost exactly
the post-Vatican II Liturgy of
the Catholic Church.
And when I heard a woman say,
"This is my body," it made the-
it made it- the freshness of
hearing a woman say that
gave the message of universality
that it always should have,
and I'm not saying it doesn't,
coming out of a male priest,
but it opened my ears to
the possibility that
it is also my body, that- that-
in my participation in
the Eucharist,
I participate in- in the gift
that Christ gives me
in a different way, because I am
not a priest, and the priest
is up there doing his thing,
you know what I mean?
He's the big boss up there,
and leading us,
and sharing this experience
with him,
but there is a hierarchical
feeling.
To hear a woman say it, who I do
not perceive of as a priest,
do you understand, it also- it
also invited me to perceive
everyone who isn't a priest as
engaging in the sacrament
in an active way, and
opened my eyes to
the message of that moment, of
both the Gospel and the Mass,
in a way that I hadn't before.
And now I invite everyone
to attack me,
for suggesting that women
should be priests.
FR. TOM: We will- your address
will be placed
at the end of this interview,
they can write directly to you.
COLBERT: Please do, please.
I got a last question for you,
I want to create a-
COLBERT: Really? That's it? I
really killed the interview with
that one. Last question,
let's get this guy out of here!
Get him out of here!
FR. TOM: I'm saving the best
for last-
[Stephen Colbert laughing]
FR. TOM: This is going to be
a long question.
Now, let's create a scenario,
the scenario is-
COLBERT: Okay, let's do it-
let's improv.
FR. TOM: Monday morning,
CBS building,
Late Night Show headquarters,
90 people around,
your team of writers,
and everybody else-
COLBERT: More than that
there, yeah.
And your three principle people,
these three wonderful women
I've been dealing with
to get you here-
COLBERT: Yes.
They come up with the idea
and say,
"Monsieur Colbert," or whatever
they call you there-
They do call me
"Monsieur Colbert", yes.
FR. TOM: Monsieur Colbert, we
want you to bring Pope Francis
onto this show.
Let's create an interview.
What would you ask Pope Francis
if he were sitting next to you
on this brand new set that you
just built at CBS,
for the Late Show-
COLBERT: I would ask him
one of the questions
you asked me, which is,
"How do you achieve joy?"
'Cause it is- it is a-
[exhales]
Well, you know joy and love,
joy I think is the expression of
the love at the moment
that you're in right now,
and the love of the person that
you're with right now.
And, uh,
I would ask him about how- how-
how love leads him to joy, or
does love lead him joy.
E. E. Cummings said, "Love is
the every only God,
who breathed this world so glad
and big." He also said that,
"Who pays any attention
to the syntax of things
will never wholly kiss you,
wholly to be a fool,
my blood approves." And so,
I would ask him about being
a fool for Christ,
because many of the things
that the Pope has said
have been seen as, I think
probably in some ways,
by people outside of the Church,
though I don't know what the
reaction is in- you know,
I'm not a member of the Curia,
as a like-
sort of bomb-throwing, you know,
but um-
because the syntax, the dogma of
the Church,
is often perceived of as the
syntax of things,
as opposed to be wholly, to be a
fool, my blood approves,
to be a fool for Christ is to
love, because we are made-
we are here to dig our brief
moment in time.
And I would ask him how he puts
that first, because
how do you get to where you are
in the Church
and not to be consumed by
the law, as opposed to
the love that led to the law.
FR. TOM: What do you think,
what do you think he would
answer you?
Just- you've been watching him
now for a couple years,
listening to him and watching
the crowd response,
what do you think's
underneath all of that?
What keeps him from being buried
under something,
or being burdened by this
wonderful tradition of ours?
I don't know, I mean I-
I mean it when I said a gift of
the Holy Spirit,
that doesn't mean something that
you don't have to work for,
I don't think, I think you have
to make a choice to
perceive Christ in the people
around you, and to
love them without fear, that
anything will be taken from you
in the gift that you give them
of your own love. Um-
The message of ultimate
sacrifice that Christ shows us
on the cross, um-
He likes people, there's
a simple way-
It helps.
COLBERT: He likes people,
he's grateful for-
maybe he's grateful
for his existence.
I think a lot of people end up
being bitter
about their own existence,
but to be grateful,
even in the face of tragedy, or
to find a great gift and
bringing comfort to others
also can, I think,
lead you to joy.
But those are all presumptuous
answers, I don't-
I don't know.
What are some of your
favourite moments?
Do you have one iconic moment,
or one favourite moment
of Pope Francis?
I like it when he spends
time with-
um-
developmentally disabled people
in St. Peter's Square.
To take the moment to-
give them dignity, of his
attention and respect, is
also very moving to me. Um-
washing the feet of a Muslim
woman on his first Good Friday,
was a very moving moment-
Holy Thursday.
COLBERT: I'm sorry,
Holy Thursday. Wow.
[Fr. Tom laughing]
I gotcha, it's the only thing
I could get you on.
COLBERT: Come on, that
was a little hostile Padre.
[laughing]
Let's do this with love. Please.
Think of Francis.
[laughing]
COLBERT: Um-
I don't know, I like that he's
laughing and smiling a lot,
you know, that's not a moment,
that's an ongoing thing.
When I was younger, I heard
Mother Teresa talk about,
and I've said this to
Jim Martin too,
Mother Teresa talked about,
you know, start your day,
smile and say "yes".
Smile and say yes. And,
I see that smile, on his face,
and it's inspirational.
And- it-
the Church is a flawed and
human institution,
for whom I always have hope.
And-
I have no doubt that he's
far from a perfect man,
but he gives me hope that
the message of joy
that he wants to spread right
now can be seen as
not revolutionary,
but a manifestation
of something that was
always there.
FR. TOM: I agree. I agree.
Stephen Colbert, I can't
thank you enough,
this was an incredible insight,
a presentation of
the new Stephen, the
born again Stephen-
[Colbert laughing]
FR. TOM: -and I think,
on one hand,
I'm more in the loss of that
previous guy, but also,
I think the world is going to
see a new Stephen,
and I think a little bit
of that previous guy
might be there too.
Oh yeah, I am a hopefully,
well-intentioned, poorly
informed, high-status idiot,
I'm not that far away from him.
FR. TOM: Welcome to the club.
COLBERT: Thanks!
FR. TOM: Thanks for joining us.
COLBERT: Thanks Father.
I have so many memories,
mostly shapes and colours.
[audience laughing]
There's a fair amount of
drinking along the way.
[audience laughing]
And as I leave you for
the last time,
I'd like to share what I've
learned with future generations,
as well as the aliens from
Zaphrax 5 who
find this show on the golden
cylinders launched into space
moments before the Earth
explodes.
[audience laughing]
Hi guys.
But you know what I'll always
remember?
The hardworking men and women
of broadcast news,
who told us who won that
governor's race.
Men and women like
Stephen Colbert.
[audience cheering]
You see folks, tonight,
tonight marks a sort of farewell
for me, but who knows,
someday maybe you'll see me
on TV again, and you'll
nudge your spouse and say,
"Hey, I remember that guy,
I used to love him. Maybe I will
buy his Slap Chop."
[audience laughing]
So, that's it for The Report,
I'll simply end by saying
it has been
a pleasure and a privilege to be
welcomed into your homes
these last nine years.
So to you, and yours, I say
a fond- what's that?
I have another month and
a half of shows?
[audience laughing]
Well then this was a little
too dramatic!
[audience laughing]
I'm sorry, we'll see you
tomorrow, I'm embarrassed!
[audience laughing]
Wow.
[audience cheering]
[theme music]
CLOSED CAPTIONING PROVIDED BY
SALT + LIGHT TELEVISION